Dragon's voice:
In a land of myth
and a time of magic,
the destiny
of a great kingdom
rests on the shoulders
of a young man.
His name: Merlin.
Even after
all these years,
I still miss him.
He was a good father.
I'm glad we came.
So am I.
I think you'd
be proud.
Particularly of elyan.
Me?
Not just because
you're a knight,
but because of
the man you've become.
- I don't think so.
- She's right.
Absolutely.
You're outstanding.
Especially when it comes
to trying to sweet-talk
the ladies,
if nothing else.
Don't listen to him.
No, elyan loves
only one woman.
- Who?
- You.
Tell me
I'm your sister.
Did Arthur not say?
Arthur never
tells me anything.
But he told you
who gwain's in love with.
- Himself.
- (Laughing)
(Incanting)
(Hissing)
(Whinnies)
They're after
the queen.
Get through the trees. Go!
(Grunts)
(Gasps)
Sleep, my lady.
For it could be some time
before you do so again.
(Theme music playing)
Merlin, hollyhock.
One dram?
And dianthus,
two drams.
- Then what?
- Three grains.
What happened?
We were riding.
We came upon
a nest of snakes.
Where's Guinevere?
Where is she?
I told her to get away.
She fled.
- Arthur!
- We ride at dawn.
Gaius: This is no accident.
Merlin: Sorcery.
Gaius: There is dark magic
coursing through their veins.
By any right
they should be dead.
They were lucky.
I fear there's
more to it than luck.
(Door closes)
Arthur: Learn to knock,
will you?
Sorry, sire.
I wanted you to know
that Leon and percival
are safe.
They are well
on the road to recovery.
That's good news.
Arthur,
there is evidence
of sorcery.
Gaius suspects
morgana is involved.
You can go, Merlin.
I lost Guinevere
once before.
You're not going
to lose her.
You're not.
We will find her.
I swear.
We'll bring her home.
Good morning,
my lady.
What do you
want with me?
I thought we could
play a little game.
A game?
To find out just
how much Arthur
loves you.
It won't work.
You underestimate
his feelings.
He's not stupid.
We'll see.
He'll know you've taken me.
He'll know it's a trap.
He will.
But he'll still come.
She must have been
knocked from her mount
with some force.
Here! Tracks.
They were heading east.
Let's go.
(Panting)
Here.
Is it too good for you
now that you're queen?
I don't want
anything from you.
Just my crown.
Drink it.
You may need it.
Why?
I wouldn't be in
such a hurry to know.
(Groans)
It's getting too dark.
We'll keep heading east.
We've lost the trail.
Then we'll
retrace the tracks.
Arthur.
I'll talk to him.
Sire?
She can't be far.
I know.
But we have to
work together.
We'll make camp
and get a fire
going.
In the morning,
we'll pick up
her trail again.
Come on.
Keep moving.
Where are
you taking me?
You'll find out.
What is this place?
Sleep well.
Morgana!
(Door locks)
(Screaming)
Elyan.
If I'd stayed
with her...
You saved percival.
You saved Leon.
But not my own
sister.
We cannot
blame ourselves.
She raised me.
You wouldn't
understand.
I do.
I don't know...
What I'd be if
it wasn't for her.
Can't explain.
You don't have to.
(Screams)
It's all right.
The tower.
It was a dream.
Everything in
its shadow is dead
and the sound,
it was like...
Like children screaming.
And the rain that fell
was like blood.
I had the same dream.
I was lost in a forest.
And the trees had claws,
and I finally
escaped it.
There was a plain.
Empty as far as
the eye could see.
- Except...
- Rising into the sky
was a black
pillar of stone.
A tower so dark
it could swallow
the sun.
Arthur: The dark tower.
It's a place where
every young knight's
taught to dread,
and rightly so.
It's where many
have met their end.
I've never heard of it.
With good reason.
It's said that
the mere mention of it
can bring doom to
any of those who hear it.
Well,
let's not
mention it again.
I was having a dream
about eating a cheese
that tasted of apple pie.
Anyone else
have that dream?
You're all
missing out.
(Sighs)
Why would they both
have that dream?
Poison.
Must still be coursing
through their veins.
But the same dream?
Arthur, morgana
conjured those snakes.
Leon and percival
would be dead if that
was what she wanted.
So what are you saying?
She planted those visions
in their minds.
It's a trap.
She's luring you
to your doom.
At the tower.
That's where she's
taken Guinevere.
(Screaming)
(Screams)
I've decided to journey
to the dark tower.
It's my belief that Guinevere's
been imprisoned there.
I don't know what
horrors will be waiting,
so I'll travel alone.
No.
I'm sorry.
I've made my decision.
You can't stop me, Arthur.
She's my sister.
Nor me, Arthur.
She's our queen.
And our friend.
She's a maiden
in a tower.
Damsel in distress.
I was born for
this moment.
You can turn back, Merlin.
I made you a promise, remember?
Arthur: The dark tower.
How do we get to it?
Through the impenetrable forest.
- But it's...
- Impenetrable.
Exactly.
We can't possibly
get through there.
We must.
(Grunts)
(Grunting)
Keep going.
(Footsteps approaching)
(Gasping)
(Gasps)
(Chuckles)
(Laughing)
(Laughter continues)
Elyan?
(Grunting)
Blunt anyway.
Don't stop.
We've lost the path.
Then we'll keep
heading north.
How do we know
which way is north?
The Ivy.
Pale leaves face south.
Dark leaves face north.
We're on
the right course.
We should reach
the tower by sundown.
We need to
pick up the pace.
Gwen.
Merlin?
- (Growls)
- (Gasps)
(Door opens)
Come.
Let us have
something to eat.
We should have made it
out of the forest by now.
Look.
What is it?
How can that be?
We have gone around
in a circle.
We have wasted
an entire day!
Let's make camp
for the night.
Get some rest.
And pick up fresh
in the morning.
I made you a promise.
Remember?
We will bring her home.
Eat. Here.
Food always makes
me feel better.
Would you prefer
some chicken?
You must eat.
You're fading away.
I don't know what cruel
trick you're playing,
but I will not be
broken by you.
I thought this
would be nice.
I know how lonely
you must be.
All by yourself
in that room.
At least you're
not shackled.
And there's daylight.
You can move.
You can see.
You expect me
to be grateful?
I too have suffered, Gwen.
I spent two years
living in darkness.
Spent two years
chained to a wall
at the bottom of a pit.
You did not know.
I would have sold my soul
for someone to show me
kindness such as this.
If you want me
to take you back up there...
(Rustling)
Welcome to my realm, emrys.
Who are you?
Why, I'm queen mab.
I am the spirit
of this place
and all the places
that bring despair
to men's hearts.
Few have ever
seen me, emrys.
You should count
yourself fortunate.
You...
Everything in in this forest.
It's bewildering.
The forest is but
one step on the journey.
How do we find
a way out?
Oh, little one,
you should not
have to ask.
Left is right
and right is left,
and the way behind
is the way ahead.
It is simple.
Oh. Simple.
You have a mind's eye,
emrys.
You must learn
to trust in it.
Far greater challenges
lie ahead.
When we reach
the dark tower?
If.
What do you mean?
You must beware, emrys.
The tower is not
a real place.
It is the heart's rest.
The mind's deepest fear.
The stillness in
the hummingbird's eye.
Stop talking
in riddles.
Then I shall
talk in rhyme.
Heed my words
with due concern,
for one of you
will not return.
What do you mean?
(Chuckles)
Which one?
We need to find the clearing
where we saw
the dolorous plains.
Which way is that?
North.
Please. I know
I can get us there.
I wouldn't do anything
to risk Gwen's life.
I can get us
to the dark tower.
I am certain.
I know what Gwen
means to you.
To all of us.
We need to head north.
Which way is that,
Merlin?
That way.
No, it's...
Over there.
How on earth
would you know that?
Sense of smell.
When the wind is from the north,
you can smell the sea.
That's ridiculous.
Trust me just this once.
Arthur,
give him a chance.
What choice do we have?
Are you sure this is
the right way, Merlin?
Come on.
Merlin...
You're a genius.
Which way now?
How far do you
think it is?
At least we
can see where
we're going.
Let's not just stand
here looking at it.
(Crying)
(Footsteps)
(Gasps)
(Screeching)
I thought you might like
to dine with me.
Come, you must eat
or you'll fade away.
(Gasps)
Your hands are cold.
There's a warm fire
going for you.
Anything you want,
you can have.
I'll give it
to you.
Why are you doing this?
Because we're friends.
- We always were.
- Leave me alone.
Gwen?
What are you trying
to do to me?
I'm helping you.
I'm looking
after you.
I want nothing from you.
Well, if you
change your mind
let me know.
(Door closes)
(Screaming)
We can't afford to rest.
I'm all right.
(Muttering, sobbing)
(Sobbing continues)
Don't look.
It'll be all right.
Merlin!
We must keep moving.
(Sobbing)
Arthur: Guinevere.
Arthur?
No.
I know it's not you.
Arthur: Guinevere.
Look at me.
I know it's not you.
Please?
It's me.
It's Arthur.
I know it's not you.
See?
It's me.
It's Arthur.
You're safe now.
(Sobs)
(Laughing)
(Screaming)
(Screaming continues)
- (Growls)
- (Screams)
It's all right.
I'm here.
My darling,
it was wrong
to make you suffer.
The mandrake root is cruel.
Pierces the depths
of your soul.
Twisting your unconscious
into the very image
you fear and dread.
Gwen, you've been
so courageous,
but it was necessary.
Gwen, you're not alone now.
You need never
be alone again.
I'm the only one
you can trust.
I'm all you have
left in the world.
The others taunt you.
Hate you.
Come.
You need some rest.
Some proper rest.
No.
Whatever twisted
game you're playing,
I want no part in it.
I would rather
stay here and die.
Something's wrong.
It's too easy.
Are you ever happy?
(Screaming)
Arthur!
(Grunting)
Aah!
No one move.
Stay exactly
where you are.
- (Grunts)
- What triggered it?
(Grunts)
The flagstones.
They must react
to pressure.
Here.
I'll use this.
I'll go first.
I'll push on.
No, elyan.
None of us would even be here
if it wasn't for me.
I have to do this.
Elyan!
Gwen.
Elyan?
What has she done to you?
No, don't.
It will not
let you pass.
Morgana has enchanted it
to protect me.
You can't free me, elyan.
Leave me here, please.
No.
You cannot
overcome it.
It will fight
to the death.
(Grunts)
(Gasps)
Elyan, go!
Save yourself.
(Clanging)
(Exhales)
- Gwen?
- Elyan?
(Grunts)
I'm here. I'm here.
I'm here.
For a moment...
I didn't think
I was gonna win.
Father would be
proud of you.
And of you.
(Chuckles)
So proud.
(Exhales)
(Sobbing)
I was warned one of us
would not return.
It's not your fault,
Merlin.
Elyan is dead.
The sword that elyan
fell prey to
was surely intended
for Arthur.
Now he's safe.
And so is Gwen.
How is it?
Arthur thinks he's won.
He has no idea.
Do you understand now
who you can trust?
It's you, morgana.
It's only ever been you.
You're not one of them,
and you never
will be.
You don't know
how much I hate them.
All of them.
You've done well
to see past the lies
to the real truth.
You have an important part
to play in the future.
Together we will ensure
the destruction
of everything
Arthur holds dear.
Merlin.
Have you noticed anything
about Gwen of late?
(Whinnies)
Arthur!
(Theme music playing)